<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Method of gaining the whole Christian world to be converts to the Church of England, by satisfying one doubt occasion'd by a request lately made to Roman-Catholics and directed to the requester.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50765</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13659659</idno>
  <idno type="VID">101071</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240900073</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1945</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1189</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">13659659</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50765)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101071)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 795:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Method of gaining the whole Christian world to be converts to the Church of England, by satisfying one doubt occasion'd by a request lately made to Roman-Catholics and directed to the requester.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([2] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Hills, printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Church of England --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term type="corporate_name">Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term type="genre_form">Broadsides --  England --  London --  17th century</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="response">
            <pb facs="tcp:101071:1"/>
            <head>A Method of Gaining the Whole Christian World to be Converts to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by satisfying one Doubt. Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion'd by <hi>a Request</hi> lately made to Roman-Catholics: and directed to the Requester.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Saw the <hi>Request</hi> you made the last week to <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholics,</hi> wherein you require an Answer to such <hi>Queries,</hi> as you have there set down touching several Points of the Doctrin and Practice of their Church. If you are a <hi>Moder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate</hi> Man, as you pretend in the Frontis-piece, it may be a satisfaction to you, to let you know, where you may find the grounds and Reasons, upon which <hi>Catholics</hi> proceed in those Points, for which you have been pleas'd to call upon them: And therefore I thought fit to give you this notice, that a day or two after your <hi>Request</hi> appear'd abroad, there was Publish'd by the King's Printer, a Book called, <hi>A Reply to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Exposition of the Doctrin of the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; in which those very Points are treated with so much Clearness, Brevity and Judgment, that I think nothing is there wanting to satisfie any Unprejudic'd Reader. There is fairly laid down the Belief of <hi>Catholics</hi> in each Point, some Proofs of <hi>Scripture</hi> upon which they build, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of <hi>Fathers</hi> and the <hi>Primitive Church</hi> confirming, and Substantial <hi>Reasons</hi> backing and supporting the whole: So that if in earnest you desire an <hi>Answer</hi> to the <hi>Queries</hi> you propose, I think I cannot recommend a fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Answer to them; Not that there is given a resolution to every demand in particular; but that the matters are there discuss'd so fully, that to one that has perus'd it seriously, and digested it, there's nothing of yours remains unanswer'd.</p>
            <p>For my own part I am to tell you, that I am a <hi>Catholic,</hi> in Communion with the <hi>See</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that I have Studied the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and <hi>Fathers;</hi> and examin'd the <hi>Practice</hi> of the <hi>Primitive Church</hi> so far, that I am thoroughly convinc'd, that the Faithful in Communion with that Church, of which I profess my self a Member, are the <hi>True Church</hi> of Christ; that Orthodox Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity is there taught, and that if I renounce <hi>this Church,</hi> I must first renounce my own Reason, which without any motives of <hi>Interest</hi> or <hi>Friends</hi> or Influence of <hi>Education</hi> obliges me to this Choice; and living in the Profession of this <hi>Faith,</hi> and in the observance of all God's <hi>Commands</hi> to the best of my Power, I hope, with the assistance of God's Grace, through the <hi>Merits</hi> and <hi>Passion</hi> of my <hi>only Redeemer</hi> Jesus Christ, to have a part in that happy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection of the Blessed, and to be Crown'd, tho' Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, with Glory.</p>
            <p>This I declare with all seriousness imaginable, and with the deepest Sense of my Soul; and in this manner I desire always to treat of <hi>Religion,</hi> and of the affairs of <hi>Eternity.</hi> For tho', upon other Subjects, a <hi>Jest</hi> or a <hi>Superficial Reasoning,</hi> may not be altogether unseasonable; yet when the <hi>Soul</hi> is concern'd, I think none of these ought to take place, much less any thing that savors of <hi>Choler,</hi> of <hi>Peevishness,</hi> of <hi>Malice</hi> or a <hi>Prejudic'd</hi> mind. Being thus dispos'd, with an unfeign'd desire of saving my Soul, I request of you to let me know, what <hi>Rule</hi> you have to propose to me, which I may follow with more safety and security, for the obtaining Salvation, than that which I now observe being a <hi>Catholic?</hi> I find in your <hi>Queries,</hi> that you severely inveigh against those you call <hi>Papists,</hi> you disapprove of their Religion, and seem perswaded, as if you had something more <hi>sound</hi> and <hi>safe</hi> for them to build on, if they would but leave that Communion, and follow your Directions. I would willingly know what this is: If you Write upon that Charitable Motive of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming your Neighbor, for his Soul's Good, let me but see a <hi>safer</hi> and a <hi>Better Rule,</hi> than that I now observe, and you may be certain of one Convert. Give me but leave to propose my Difficulties; and your Instructions af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, if in order to a <hi>Better Light,</hi> will be very welcome.</p>
            <p>And in the first place I must assure you, as I now am, I desire to follow the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and that so Religiously, that I pretend to <hi>observe</hi> and <hi>Believe</hi> all that is there <hi>Commanded</hi> and <hi>Taught:</hi> And as zealously to <hi>depart</hi> from all, that I understand to be there <hi>forbidden</hi> me. So that in this Point, I think, all Directions will be needless; since, I am satisfied, I have, being now a <hi>Papist,</hi> so great a Veneration in my Soul for that <hi>Sacred Volume,</hi> that I do not see you can make any additions to it.</p>
            <p>All the difficulty will be about the <hi>True Sense</hi> of the <hi>Scripture.</hi> And here, if you have any thing to say, it must be upon this Point: For whilst I embrace the <hi>Book,</hi> as <hi>Divine,</hi> and as the <hi>Written Word of God,</hi> and have a true desire of following it; if I am not in the <hi>True way,</hi> it must be, because I mistake the <hi>True Sense</hi> and <hi>Meaning</hi> of it. So that in order to reduce me, if I am in an Error, you must point to me some <hi>better</hi> and <hi>more certain Means</hi> of being assured of the <hi>True Sense</hi> of the <hi>Scripture,</hi> than I now follow being a <hi>Papist.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you allow me a <hi>Liberty of Judging,</hi> and that as I am a <hi>Private Person,</hi> I must use the the <hi>Judgment of Discretion,</hi> and follow it according to the best of my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son; I must tell you before hand, that this will work no Reformation i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> me. Because as I am now in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> I <hi>Read</hi> and <hi>Scarch</hi> the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> I examin and confer Places, and make use of all the <hi>Liberty of Judging</hi> I can desire; and after all, my own <hi>Private Reason</hi> assures me, that I now follow the <hi>Scriptures;</hi> that I understand them in the <hi>True Sense,</hi> and that if my own <hi>Judgment of Discretion</hi> is to lead me into the <hi>Truth</hi> of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> I now live and believe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that Truth, since I believe nothing, but what in my own Private Judgment I am convinc'd to be True.</p>
            <p>If you would have me take along with me the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Sense of the <hi>Primitive Church,</hi> as it is found in the Antient <hi>Fathers,</hi> the most <hi>Authentic Witnesses</hi> of those Purer times, and, by the help of their Writings, examin the Holy Scriptures; this I have done already; and if you'l allow me to take them according to the best of my own <hi>Private Reason</hi> and <hi>Understanding,</hi> I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suaded, that the Religion I now Profess, is what they recommend, and what they deliver as the Belief of those more Apostolical times.</p>
            <p>If you will have me not rest altogether in my own <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Judgment</hi> in the <hi>understanding</hi> the <hi>Scriptures</hi> and <hi>Fathers,</hi> but that I receive instruction and direction from some <hi>Teachers,</hi> or <hi>Guides;</hi> You must tell me, who these <hi>Guides</hi> must be? why rather <hi>Church-of-England Guides,</hi> than <hi>Lutherans, Calvinists, Socinians;</hi> or why not Those of my own Communion? I am persuaded that amongst any of these may be found men as <hi>Learned,</hi> as <hi>Vertuous,</hi> as <hi>Sincere,</hi> as <hi>Exemplar</hi> in their Conversation, as Those of the <hi>Church of England.</hi> How then shall I be certain of being better instructed in the <hi>true sense</hi> of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and having a greater Assurance of my Salvation, from following <hi>Church-of-England-Guides,</hi> than Those of any other Communion, even of that of which I am at present a Member? And then, by what means shall I come to be convinc'd, that the <hi>Church-of-England-Guides</hi> are those who will most certainly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct me in the <hi>Truth</hi> of the <hi>Scriptures?</hi> They have no <hi>Miracles</hi> to recommend them before others. And then for the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> I cannot be assur'd of it by them; because (according to your own way of arguing) the <hi>true sense</hi> of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> is the thing at present under debate; and for this (as is suppos'd here) I must depend upon the Instruction of the <hi>true Guides:</hi> How then can the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures certainly tell me, which are <hi>These Guides,</hi> when, it seems, I cannot be certain of the <hi>true sense</hi> of Scripture, till I have found <hi>Those Guides?</hi> This is nothing but that viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Circle so often reprov'd by you; <hi>viz. the proving the Guides by Scripture; and the Scripture by the Guides.</hi> And this will further oblige you to satisfie another diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of your own: That if I, interpreting Scripture by my own <hi>private judgment,</hi> can find which are the <hi>True Guides;</hi> why can't I by the same means find out in the Scriptures all other Necessaries to Salvation? And then what need of Guides at all? since 'tis certain the finding out the <hi>True Guides</hi> is none of the easiest Points, amongst such an infinit Number of Pretenders.</p>
            <p>If you will have me <hi>submit</hi> my <hi>Judgment of Dis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to what is determin'd in matters of Religion by <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic consent,</hi> and establish'd by the <hi>Authority of a Church;</hi> you must demonstrate to me, why this must be the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> before others. You cannot but know, that as I am now, I have <hi>public con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent,</hi> and the <hi>Authority</hi> of a <hi>Church,</hi> for what I believe: and if the submission to <hi>Authority</hi> be necessary for the finding the Truth, why may not this <hi>Authority</hi> be that of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> rather than of <hi>England?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You endeavor to prove indeed, that the <hi>Authority</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is not <hi>Infallible</hi> in its direction; and▪
<pb facs="tcp:101071:2"/> could you make good what you pretend, yet this would be no reason for me to withdraw my self from that <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> and submit to that of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> because, were it <hi>Fallible,</hi> as you say, yet would it be still, as to this point, upon equal terms with Yours, which you own to be <hi>Fallible</hi> too: And of Two <hi>Fallible Authorities,</hi> what reason have I to forsake the <hi>One,</hi> to follow the <hi>Other?</hi> Nay, were the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> as <hi>Fallible</hi> as you would have her, that is, as Your own <hi>Church of England;</hi> yet should I still think my self in <hi>Reason</hi> oblig'd to submit to the <hi>Former;</hi> because, tho' suppos'd to be <hi>Fallible,</hi> 'tis yet a much <hi>Greater Authority</hi> than the <hi>Other;</hi> whil'st the <hi>Church of England,</hi> having but the Authority of <hi>One Nation,</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> has an <hi>Authority</hi> more <hi>Universal,</hi> and of <hi>many Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and of <hi>many Ages</hi> too. And certainly, when <hi>Two Authorities</hi> are propos'd that are <hi>Fallible,</hi> I think, as I am a rational Creature, I am oblig'd to accept of the <hi>Greater.</hi> This I am bound to in all other Cases, and why not in this? Especially, when there's nothing of <hi>Learning, Piety,</hi> or <hi>Sincerity</hi> wanting in the <hi>Greater,</hi> which should make the <hi>Lesser</hi> preferable. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this case, when all <hi>Assemblies</hi> of <hi>Bishops</hi> are suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to be subject to <hi>Error,</hi> and yet my Submission is exacted to the <hi>Determinations</hi> of some of them; why should I choose to follow the decision of <hi>Six and Twenty,</hi> rather than of <hi>Three, Four, Five,</hi> or <hi>Six Hundred?</hi> And yet this you would have me do; if you persuade me rather to hear the Church of <hi>England</hi> than the Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rch of <hi>Rome.</hi> You know, when Difficulties are propos'd to a <hi>Council,</hi> the Members whereof are equally <hi>Discerning, Wise,</hi> and <hi>Prudent,</hi> 'tis most justifiable and safe, in case of disagreement, to follow the Majority of Votes: and if there should be <hi>Three or Four Hundred</hi> on the <hi>one side,</hi> and only <hi>Six and Twenty</hi> on the <hi>other;</hi> it could not be excused from a rash and inconsiderate Act, to leave the <hi>Greater Authority,</hi> and submit to the <hi>Less.</hi> Upon what Motives then, when the Concern is about <hi>Authority,</hi> can you persuade me to prefer the <hi>Lesser?</hi> I am for going upon the <hi>surest</hi> Grounds, and cannot tell how to choose that in the affair of my <hi>Soul,</hi> which in any <hi>Temporal</hi> concern I should condemn as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudent.</p>
            <p>If you urge against the Authority of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> (as you have done in your <hi>Queries)</hi> that she has confirm'd <hi>Definitions</hi> and <hi>Decrees</hi> plainly <hi>contradictory</hi> to one another; I confess this would sufficiently lessen her Authority, could it be prov'd, which I have never seen done hitherto. And yet, were it made out evidently and clearly, I don't think this would be any reason for any considering man to submit to the Authority of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> rather than to Her; because the Authority of the Church of <hi>England</hi> has much greater Failings to diminish Her than This. For here I desire you to consider what is the <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Church of England?</hi> 'Tis nothing but the Authority of this <hi>One Nation,</hi> as it appears in her Representatives assembled together, both Ecclesiastical and Civil, under their Head and Supreme Governor. All the Authority it has is comprehended in This; and if I am requir'd to submit to or rely on <hi>Her Authority,</hi> 'tis to submit to what is thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd by <hi>Public Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt,</hi> and establish'd in such an <hi>Assembly.</hi> Now I here demand, whether <hi>this Authority</hi> has not much more to discourage me from relying on it, in matters of <hi>Religion,</hi> than all that is objected against the <hi>Authority</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> For what is all you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ge to diminish the <hi>Authority</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and dissuade me from relying on it? 'Tis Her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming Definitions contradictory to one another, as you pretend, but without evident proof. And what is this in what appears in dis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>avor of the <hi>Authority</hi> of the Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>h of <hi>England,</hi> which has not only confirm'd <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ry Doctrines,</hi> but even alter'd the whole Frame of <hi>Religion</hi> several t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mes, set up and pull'd down; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>'d a Religion to be <hi>Orthodox,</hi> and establish'd it accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Law; then declar'd the same to be <hi>not Orthodox,</hi> but to be persecuted according to Law, and this by <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic Council, of the same Persons, who had so lately esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish'd it:</hi> then again declar'd it to be <hi>Orthodox</hi> a second <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>e, and what was just before set up by the <hi>public Council</hi> of the Nation, as the only <hi>True Religion,</hi> was now by the same Council made <hi>Criminal,</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> allotted for those that should embrace it. So that Dr. <hi>South,</hi> in a Sermon preach'd at <hi>Lincolns-Inn,</hi> observes upon this Subject, (p. 83.) <hi>That in the space of twelve years, there were four Changes about Religion made in</hi> England, <hi>and that by the</hi> PUBLIC COUNCIL <hi>and</hi> AUTHORITY <hi>of the R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alm, which were more</hi> (says he) <hi>than were made by any Christian State throughout the World in Fifteen Hundred years before.</hi> And then, with some sense of this Frailty, he adds by way of complaint, That <hi>hence it is the Enemies of God take occasion to blaspheme, and call our Religion</hi> STATISM: <hi>and now adding to the former those many Changes that have happened since, I am afraid</hi> (says he) <hi>we shall never be able to claw off that Name.</hi> So that as far as I see, even Your own Men acknowledge far greater Failings in the <hi>Authority</hi> upon which <hi>Your Church</hi> stands <hi>establish'd,</hi> than even what you offer at to prove against That of the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> whil'st It has made more <hi>contradictory Decrees</hi> in matters of <hi>Religion</hi> in <hi>Twelve</hi> Years, than ever was done by any other Christian State in <hi>Fifteen hundred.</hi> What reason then can I have to distrust the <hi>Authority</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and rely upon that of the Church of <hi>England?</hi> If you would not have me submit my <hi>Judgment of Discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to the <hi>public Consent</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> because you pretend <hi>That Authority</hi> has confirm'd <hi>contrary Definitions:</hi> how shall I submit to the <hi>Authority</hi> upon which the Church of <hi>England</hi> stands; when I see <hi>this Authority,</hi> not by the Pretences of <hi>Adversaries,</hi> but by the Concession of <hi>Her own Members,</hi> and upon Record, has so often confirm'd <hi>contradictory Religions?</hi> The same <hi>public Consent,</hi> and the same <hi>full Authority,</hi> consenting to and approving those <hi>different Religions,</hi> which you would have me now submit to, and rely on, in behalf of the <hi>Doctrin</hi> and <hi>Practices</hi> of <hi>Your Church.</hi> But what trusting, in matters of <hi>Religion,</hi> to such an <hi>Authority,</hi> which is so <hi>contradictory</hi> to it self? I tell you truly, I should not take up the Religion of which I am now a Member, upon <hi>this Authority;</hi> how then can I rely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it for the Truth of <hi>Yours?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this nature I apprehend Affairs to stand relating to Religion. The only concern being about the <hi>True Sense and Interpretation of Scripture.</hi> And this you must speak plain to, if you would gain me and the whole Christian World Converts. I find you take great pains in raising Difficulties against the <hi>Religion</hi> of your <hi>Neighbors;</hi> this is the Subject of your <hi>Queries,</hi> this I see done in many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Tracts that come abroad, in which with much Bitterness and Virulency their <hi>Prelates</hi> are Revil'd, their <hi>Doctrins</hi> Ridicul'd, the Frailties of past Ages are ript up, and all kind of Indignities fixt upon the present Profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors, with no more Signs of Charity, than if <hi>Christians</hi> were <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Turks</hi> to each other; this I see and not without some resentment, for the scandal it reflects upon our Common Christianity: But all this you do, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Raising of Dust, 'tis all <hi>Pulling down,</hi> but no <hi>Building up.</hi> If you are certain, that <hi>Catholics</hi> and all other <hi>Dissenters</hi> from you are in the <hi>Wrong,</hi> pray be so Charitable to us, to shew us the <hi>Right.</hi> But do it like <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Christians;</hi> convince us by clear and evident Reason; without <hi>Flirting, Jeering</hi> or <hi>Reviling.</hi> And this you may do in short, whilst we desire to be satisfied in <hi>One</hi> Point only, <hi>viz. How we shall be assured of the True Sense and Meaning of the Holy Scriptures.</hi> This Point alone when clearly prov'd and explicated, will put an end to <hi>Controversie,</hi> with all Good and well-meaning Christians. Let us therefore know, whether in <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the Scriptures,</hi> we are wholly to rely, under God, upon our own <hi>Private Judgment of Discretion.</hi> Or if we are to suppose a <hi>Competent Instruction</hi> from some <hi>Teachers;</hi> and in understanding <hi>Obscure Texts of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and the more <hi>difficult Points of Religion,</hi> to rely upon <hi>Guides;</hi> shew us who these <hi>Teachers</hi> and <hi>Guides</hi> must be? Why Those of the <hi>Church of</hi> England as E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stablish'd by <hi>Law,</hi> above all others? Or lastly, if we are to submit to what is determin'd by Public Consent, and Establish'd by the <hi>Authority</hi> of a <hi>Church;</hi> let us know why <hi>this Church,</hi> must be that which is at present Establish'd by <hi>Law;</hi> more than That which was Estab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish'd formerly, by the <hi>same Authority,</hi> or any other. Satisfie us but in this, by clear and Evident Proofs, and you gain us all. You cannot but think, that amongst all sorts of <hi>Dissenters,</hi> there are many serious, and well-meaning Persons, who have a true desire of saving their Souls; such who endeavor to follow the Truth of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and would not depart from what they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand to be there deliver'd, upon no Worldly account whatsoever: And if they are in an <hi>Error,</hi> 'tis because they <hi>mistake</hi> the <hi>Sense</hi> of that <hi>Sacred Rule.</hi> What there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can you do better than to give Direction in order to the rectifying these Mistakes, and assign them a Method, by which they shall <hi>certainly</hi> find the <hi>Truth</hi> of all the <hi>Mysteries</hi> of Christianity there deliver'd, and taught? This is but <hi>One</hi> single Point to be resolv'd, which if done Plainly, Briefly, and Satisfactorily, will certainly more contribute to the healing the Divisions of Christendom, and uniting us in one Belief, than all the Two-hundred Queries you have propos'd in your <hi>Request.</hi> And in this performance, as you will highly oblige all sincere and Well-meaning Persons, so most Particularly.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir, </salute>
               <signed>Yours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hills,</hi> Printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty for His Houshold and Chappel; And are to be sold at his Printing-house on the Ditch-side in <hi>Black-Fryers.</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>